# **Nathan Ryley Tharp**

Tyler, TX | NRTharp24@gmail.com | 903-253-4987 nrtharp.github.io | linkedin.com/in/nathan-ryley-tharp

#### **OBJECTIVE:**

Motivated, dedicated, and reliable recent mechanical engineering graduate pursuing an immediate position with an innovative engineering company and willing to relocate. Seeking to integrate 18 years of diligent work experience with engineering skills from academic and freelance projects to further a passion for the advancement of mankind.

#### SKILLS:

SolidWorks and AutoCAD Engineering Design Leadership and Decision-Making Skills ANSYS Fluent and MATLAB Systems Analysis Strong Work Ethic and Teamwork Skills

GD&T Product Assembly Outstanding Presentation Skills

Microsoft Office Suite Technical Reporting Exceptional Written and Verbal Communication

Programming Troubleshooting Self-Starter and Self-Teacher

## **EDUCATION:**

University of Texas at Tyler, Tyler, Texas Graduated: 05/2020

Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering - Cumulative G.P.A.: 3.4

#### **EXPERIENCE:**

University of Texas at Tyler (Tyler, TX)

## **Team Lead – Gait Rehabilitation Device, 07/2019 – 05/2020**

- · Conducted research in the bio-mechanical field and found that the market was lacking rehabilitation hardware at an affordable cost for victims of stroke or spinal cord injury
- · Developed manufacturing strategies for an electro-mechanical system using 2D and 3D CAD modeling software, consisting of electric motors, aluminum linkages, and microcontrollers
- · Verified customer specifications using FEA techniques in ANSYS and SolidWorks
- Generated documentation and developed presentations for training and design review using Microsoft Office Software Suite and SolidWorks Visualize, leading to a polished and professional demonstration
- Maintained a network of accountability in a multidisciplinary group and delegated specific tasks to ensure completion of deliverables ahead of schedule and within budget
- · Self-taught SolidWorks, SolidWorks Visualize, ANSYS, and Autodesk Inventor to complete project to the high standard set for the team, and furthered a passion for design and analysis
- · Completed project on schedule and 40% under budget despite setbacks due to Coronavirus

## Team Lead - Powered Lift, 01/2019 - 05/2019

- Designed and manufactured a powered jack that lifted 100 times more than the minimum requirement leading to the team earning 1st place against 10 competing teams
- $\cdot$  Project remained within budget and ahead of schedule due to networking and effective management

# **Team Lead – Walking Robot, 08/2018 – 12/2018**

- · Designed, assembled, and wired a 6-legged walking robot for both speed and agility which earned 1st place in competition against 8 teams by traversing a course the fastest
- · Enjoyed overcoming obstacles, as well as gaining experience in robotics which aided in future endeavors
- · Completed project 1 month ahead of schedule due to excellent team coordination, allowing for further optimization and providing the edge necessary to supersede the design of other teams

#### Team Lead – CO2 Sensor, 08/2018 – 12/2018

- · Developed a CO2 sensor which managed airflow into a room by manipulating a damper for use in demand control ventilation systems for the HVAC industry, leading to greater efficiency and lower consumer cost
- · Self-taught Arduino coding language and developed an excitement for programming which persists to today

## **Team Member - Cable Camera**, 01/2018 - 05/2018

- · Assisted in development of a cable camera for use in recreational or professional videography
- · Generated a design presentation video to convey design, specifications, and uses to customers
- · Utilized outside resources to learn Adobe Premiere Pro which increased quality of presentations

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE:**

Bernard's Mediterranean Restaurant (Tyler, TX)

#### Server and Bartender, 02/2015 – 05/2016 and 02/2017 – 05/2020

Provided excellent customer service and guided a unique dining experience utilizing presentation skills and
effective interpersonal communication to drive sales and elevate customer satisfaction which directly led to
repeat business and lasting relationships

The Grove Restaurant (Tyler, TX)

## Head Server, 04/2016 – 02/2017

· Oversaw operations of fellow servers, handled minor customer complaints, and delegated daily duties while simultaneously performing server duties and caring for the most distinguished guests

Chuy's Tex-Mex Restaurant (Tyler, TX and Arlington, TX)

#### Server, 02/2013 – 01/2014 and 09/2014 – 02/2015

 Provided customer service and utilized effective presentation and interpersonal communication skills to drive sales and elevate customer satisfaction. Often topped sales competitions and received commendations for prompt and polite service

Centene Corporation (Tyler, TX)

# Advanced Claims Analyst, 01/2014 - 08/2014

 Utilized Microsoft Excel and Access to analyze payments of medical insurance claims often exceeding \$1,000,000 daily and completed claims up to 3 times faster than others in the department while maintaining greater than 99% accuracy and zero audits

MotoPhoto Portrait Studio and Photo Lab (Tyler, TX)

## Lead Lab Technician, 06/2008 – 02/2013

 Maintained industry grade printers and performed quality control leading to community trust and repeat business for a small company, resulting in annual profits in excess of \$300,000

Andy's Frozen Custard (Tyler, TX)

## Machine Operator, 05/2007 - 03/2008

· Maintained production of custard and regulated output based on demand, while ensuring safe practices and sanitation

Target (Tyler, TX) – Seasonal

#### Cashier, 10/2006 – 01/2007

· Performed cashier duties with speed and efficiency to limit customer dissatisfaction and maintain a steady revenue flow, often handling greater than \$10,000 in products per shift

PC-ER (Tyler, TX)

# Computer Repair Technician, 05/2006 – 07/2007

 Designed and assembled consumer-grade computers to customer specifications and repaired defunct computers by troubleshooting and replacing hardware as needed, often handling multiple projects simultaneously

Tyler Junior College (Tyler, TX) – Work Study

# Administrative Assistant, 08/2005 - 05/2006

 $\cdot$  Maintained student records, answered telephones, and directed students to educational resources Subway (Tyler, TX and Katy, TX) – Seasonal

#### Sandwich Maker, 05/2004 – 08/2004 and 11/2005 – 02/2006

 $\cdot \ \, \text{Provided customer service, performed food preparation, and maintained a clean work environment} \\ \, \text{Dairy Queen (Katy, TX)} - \text{Seasonal}$ 

## Counter Help, 05/2003 – 08/2003

· Provided customer service, handled multiple operations simultaneously, and maintained cash drawer 21st Century Systems (Katy, TX) – Seasonal

# Installation Technician, 05/2002 – 08/2002 and 05/2003 – 08/2003

 Installed high performance home theater equipment, security systems, whole-house audio, and ethernet lines both during and post-construction while ensuring continuity of various integrated systems with budgets for the projects often exceeding \$50,000